\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CSCI-903: Information and Intelligence
Syllabus

Course Description

What, I hear you ask, do information and intelligence have to do with each other? And what, you might also ask, do they have to do with computer science?
The short answer: information theory is one of the key underpinnings of computer science, and artificial intelligence is a key area of computer science that owes its success to careful exploitation of the principles of information theory (among others).

The longer answer is why we have an entire semester devoted to this “special topic” course!

The course will be conducted in seminar form: students will play an active role in the course, and will each be responsible for leading some of the discussions and activities in the course. The goal here is for you to learn to organize and express your understanding of some complex, but interesting, topics.

There are two main readings for the course, the first two items in the Texts section below. As its title suggests, the Gleick book deals with information theory. Don’t let the word “theory” put you off: despite information theory’s basis in mathematics, Gleick presents the material without assuming any particular mathematical spohistication, yet without watering down its essence. The Christian book is written at a level that assumes no more preparation than a willingness to think about and evaluate ideas that might be new to you. Coincidentally, the two books were published within a month of each other early in 2011.

The course requires a regular time committment from you: because of the seminar format, you have to be prepared for each class (especially the ones where you lead part of the discussion!), and you will be required to complete a small (1-2 page) writing assignment each week.

In addition to reading, discussing, and writing about course topics, there is another course component: coding. Writing code is emerging as a valuable skill for artists, social and natural scientists, business people, and professionals of all types. This course does not aim to make you into a programmer, but will use one or more coding exercises as a way to reinforce the principles of information theory and artificial intelligence you will be wrestling with during the semester.

Course Objectives

Students who complete this course successfully will be able to:

Explain the relationship between information and information codes.
Explain the differences among data, information, and knowledge.
Describe the model underlying the concept of an “intelligent agent.”
Give examples of artificial intelligence in daily life.
Discuss the relationships among information, probabilities, and search strategies.
Write code to implement the algorithm for an elementary intelligent agent.

Instructor

The instructor for the course is Dr. Christopher Vickery. See Dr. Vickery’s Contact Information and Office Hours for that information.

Course Structure and Assessment

The following information is not specific to this course.
Details to follow ...

There are two 75 minute class meetings per week. Attendance will not be taken (except at the beginning of the semester to verify your registration for the course), but students who often miss class will probably fail the course. The reading assignments for the course are listed below, and will be broken down further in the course schedule page for the semester.

Assignments

Grading

Grades are posted on the web as soon as they are available.

Exam and assignment grades become permanent one week after they have been posted, even if there has been a scoring error. Be sure to check that your exam was scored correctly and that the correct grade has been recorded (using the “Check My Grades” form on the course schedule page) as soon as exams are returned.

The College has a standard policy for converting course averages into letter grades, which I follow mechanically, except I compute fractional course averages and round to the nearest integer, which gives you half a point of automatic grade inflation. For example, the college policy specifies a grade of B+ for course averages between 87 and 90: because of rounding, that means that any score between 86.5 and 89.5 is a B+.

Texts

James Gleick, The Information. Pantheon, 2011. ISBN-13: 978-0375423727
Brian Christian, The Most Human Human. Doubleday, 2011. ISBN-13: 978-0385533065
Edward Tufte, Beautiful Evidence, Graphics Press, 2006. ISBN-13: 978-0961392178

Notes:

Both the Gleick and Christian books are available in electronic format. Both are required.
Prof. Tufte has offerred to make copies of Beautiful Evidence available to students in this course for $10 each (below cost).

Vickery Home—XHTML—CSS—Last updated

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CSCI-903: Script Programming for the Web
Syllabus

This syllabus gives the intended structure and requirements for this course, but the actual topics and amount of time spent on each topic varies from semester to semester. The course schedule for this semester, including exam dates and assignments to be handed in, is on this semester’s schedule page.

Course Objectives

The target for application development has evolved from the mainframe, to the desktop, to the web, and to mobile devices. Even with the advent of massively parallel computing systems, the basic principle that threads of execution implement algorithmic processes remains consistently applicable regardless of the target environment.

This course is designed as a first course in algorithmic computing for non-computer science majors. Although the course is open to computer science majors, the only prerequisite is familiarity with code development for basic web technologies: XHTML and CSS.

Although the ‘L’ in XHTML stands for “language,” neither XHTML nor CSS is an algorithmic programming language. Rather, they are declarative languages: they tell what content to display and what the content should look like. With the exception of some important pseudo-classes in CSS (:hover, :checked, etc.) they do not provide a way to specify the dynamic behavior of web pages, and they certainly do not provide a way to specify the procedural richness needed to create dynamic web applications.

The course introduces students to algorithmic programming using two scripting languages widely used for web applications: PHP and JavaScript. Because web applications typically draw parts of their content from online databases, the course will introduce students to PHP’s facilities for interacting with database systems.

Students who complete this course successfully will be able to:

Explain the structure of the HTTP protocol for exchanging messages over the Internet
Identify the features of web servers needed to support PHP and a local database
Tell how the Unix shell allows users to implement sequential algorithms using pipelines constructed from a set of filter programs
Define the terms standard input, standard output, read, and write in the context of Unix filter programs

Use PHP and JavaScript language constructs: variables, functions, objects, control structures, and data types.

Use PHP to query and update a database using SQL
Implement event-driven algorithms in JavaScript
Use JSON and XMLHttpRequest objects to exchange information between PHP and JavaScript code
To use PHP to generate DOM elements and JavaScript to manage DOM elements of a web page

Instructor

The instructor for the course is Dr. Christopher Vickery. See Dr. Vickery’s Contact Information and Office Hours for that information.

Course Structure and Assessment

There are two 75 minute class meetings per week. Attendance will not be taken (except at the beginning of the semester to verify your registration for the course), but students who often miss class will probably fail the course. The reading assignments for the course are listed below, and will be broken down further in the course schedule page for the semester.

Assignments

The course is based on a series of programming assignments, which may be coded and tested in the Computer Science Department’s TREE Lab using Dreamweaver and other development tools available in the lab to manage the web site used for your projects.

If you prefer, you may do your coding assignments outside the lab, provided you write the code according to the specifications given in the assignments.

In addition to your laboratory account, you will use a limited “shell account” on babbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu that you will use for testing and remote sites for your assignments. You will submit assignments for the course by uploading your code to a public server on babbage.

Assignments vary in complexity: simple assignments receive a full-credit grade of “ok” provided they are simply submitted on time and meet standard requirements for the assignment. Assignments receive half credit if they are submitted within one calendar week of the due date (“late”)‚ or if they are deficient in some way (“not ok”). A grade of “good” (extra credit) is possible, as are the grades of “late not ok” (quarter credit) and “too late” (no credit, but instructor feedback provided).

More complicated assignments are graded on a ten-point scale. The relative weights of the small and larger assignments vary from term to term. Assignments count 40% of the course grade.

All code submitted must use valid XHTML5 and CSS3, as verified by the W3C validators, in order to receive full credit. Certain warnings from the validators are acceptable; these exceptions vary from semester to semester, depending on the status of the validators themselves.

Each web page you submit for this course must contain the following code as the last element in the body element:

<footer> <a href="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=referer">XHTML</a> — <a href="http://jigsaw.w3.org/css-validator/check/referer?profile=css3">CSS</a> </footer>

Exams

There will be two exams, a midterm and a final, which will each count 30% of your course average.

Grading

Grades are posted on the web as soon as they are available.

Exam and assignment grades become permanent one week after they have been posted, even if there has been a scoring error. Be sure to check that your exam was scored correctly and that the correct grade has been recorded (using the “Check My Grades” form on the course schedule page) as soon as exams are returned.

The College has a standard policy for converting course averages into letter grades, which I follow mechanically, with two exceptions: (a) I compute fractional course averages and round to the nearest integer, which gives you half a point of automatic grade inflation. For example, the college policy specifies a grade of B+ for course averages between 87 and 90: because of rounding, that means that any score between 86.5 and 89.5 is a B+. (b) Because a grade of C- (or less) cannot be counted towards the computer science major, I let my personal judgment (based primarily on class attendance and participation) influence how to handle course grades that are just below 71.5. But I do not automatically raise C– grades to C.

Reference Material

There is no textbook for this course, but there are numerous excellent resources available that deal with the topics covered, including both print and web media.

For the PHP language

,

the online manual at php.net provides well-organized and authoritative information, with additional annotations and examples from practitioners in the field.

There are many PHP books available, several of which include material on SQL access to databases from within PHP scripts. Many of these books are based on the “case study” method of exposition, which can be terrific if you are trying to learn the material on your own. However this course has it’s own set of case studies (assignments), and it can be difficult to use these books in conjunction with the course. Some books to consider, in no particular order, include:

Build Your Own Database Driven Web Site Using PHP & MySQL

by Kevin Yank, available from Sitepoint.

PHP/MySQL

by Joel Murach and Ray Harris, available from Murach’s.

PHP Solutions

by David Powers, available from Friends of Ed.

Learning PHP, MySQL, and JavaScript

by Robin Nixon, available from O’Reilly

Each of these publishers is highly regarded, and it is well worth while looking at their other offerings in the field.

For the JavaScript language

,

you might want to consider these:

JavaScript and jQuery

by Zak Ruvalcaba and Mike Murach. Excellent range of topics; starts at the beginning. (Murach’s)

Secrets of the JavaScript Ninja

by John Resig (developer of the jQuery library) and Bear Bibeault. More advanced than the Murach book, but “the” place to go to become a highly effective JavaScript developer. (Manning Publications)

JavaScript: The Good Parts

by Douglas Crockford. Highly authoritative author. (O’Reilly)

DOM Scripting

by Jeremy Keith. (Friends of Ed)

JavaScript and DOM Scripting

by Ray Harris. (Murach’s)

Simply JavaScript

by Kevin Yank and Cameron Adams. (SitePoint)

Topics

Here is an idealized schedule of topics and assignments for the course. The actual assignments vary from semester to semester.

Classes | Topics | Assignments
1-2 | Web Structures and the UNIX programming model | Verify lab account; set up web site for the course
3-4 | Browsers, Servers, Databases, and the HTTP Protocol | The PHP programming model: headers and generated content
5-7 | PHP Programing: Syntax and Debugging | Display PHP data types; calculate values
8-9 | PHP Programming: Strings, Arrays, and Form Data | Respond to form submission
10 | PHP Programming: Session Management | User login without database
11 | PHP Programming: Regular Expressions | Parse user input
12-13 | PHP Programming: Database CRUD and SQL Injection Attacks | User registration and login
14 | Midterm Exam
15-16 | JavaScript Programming: Syntax and Debugging | Display variable types
17-18 | JavaScript Programming: The DOM | Change the class of DOM elements
19-20 | JavaScript Programming: Event Handling | Respond to clicks and keystrokes
21-22 | JavaScript Programming: Form Enhancement | Validate form submission
23-24 | AJAX: Using XMLHttpRequests and JSON | Validate input against selection list
25-28 | Final Project Design and Implementation | Final Project
| Final Exam

Vickery Home—XHTML—CSS—Last updated

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

Script Programming For The Web
Dr. Vickery

Introduction

There are four elements of a typical web site that this course is designed to pull together: content markup (XHTML), content presentation (CSS), user—browser interaction (JavaScript) and content management (PHP/SQL). The prerequisite for this course is Computer Science 081 or the equivalent, which should have given you a firm grounding in XHTML and CSS.

JavaScript is a programming language that is available in all browsers as well as several other applications, including Photoshop, OpenOffice, and Flash (where it is called ActionScript). In all these environments, JavaScript is used to extend and customize the behavior of the base application. In the case of browsers, JavaScript can be used to validate information entered by users locally before submitting that information to a remote server, as well as to provide many forms of user interaction that go beyond those available using CSS. JavaScript is the 'J' in AJAX.

Content management refers to a combination of programs and a database that run on a remote server, often the same server that delivers web pages when the user clicks on a link. Server-side programs can be written in any programming language; in this course you will work with PHP, a scripting language largely derived from an earlier scripting language, Perl. PHP is the most widely used server-side scripting language in use today; other popular languages (besides Perl) are Ruby, Python, and Java. (Java, by the way, has nothing to do with JavaScript.)

There are several database systems that can be used for managing content: Oracle is widely used on very large corporate and shopping web sites; MySQL, owned by Sun Microsystems, is an extremely popular system that is available at no cost. We will use PostgreSQL for our databases. It is free and open source, and historically has had a better feature set than MySQL. This course concentrates on JavaScript and PHP programming, so the choice of which database system we use will have little impact on your work in the course.

There is a laboratory in the Computer Science Department where we have Apache web servers with PHP support installed, access to PostgreSQL databases (one for each student), and industry standard development tools like Dreamweaver. You use the computers in the lab any time the college is open, and you can log into them remotely from off campus anytime, 24/7. Alternatively, you can set up Apache/PHP/PostgreSQL on your own computer, do your assignments there, and then upload your assignments to your account in the lab for final testing and submission.

Topics

The following is a generic list of topics for the course. The actual schedule of assignments and exams is given in this semester’s course web page.

Class Numbers | Topics
1 |

Introduction to Scripting Languages

Compilers, Emulators, and Interpreters
Shell Scripting: Bash; Cmd.exe, …
CGI Scripting: Perl, …
Scripting Languages: JavaScript; PHP; Ruby; Python, …
Libraries and Frameworks
Scripting, Web Standards, and Accessibility

2 |

Web Site Structure And Operations

Client-Server Model: Internet message passing; hosts; ports
The Apache Server: Configuration file; modules; log files
DocumentRoot
Subdirectories: css, scripts, images
Life-cycle of a web request from browser’s perspective
Server request processing: server-side scripting

3-10 |

Client-Side Scripting

script tags, scripts directories, and .js script files. jsmin and jslint.
Embedded JavaScript — Not!
Values: numbers; strings; references; booleans
Variables, Expressions, Statements, Functions, Arrays, and Objects
Events: handlers vs listeners; managing
Control Structures
DOM Interactions: Form verification; Dynamic Effects
Debugging/Optimizing with FireBug

11 | Midterm Exam
12-20 |

Server-Side Scripting

Server Processing (Apache): embedding in XHTML documents; code scope; generating response headers
Variables, Expressions, Functions, Arrays, Objects, Classes
Control Structures
Receiving and sanitizing form data.

21-28 |

Client-Server Script Interactions

XMLHTTPRequest Processing
JSON Processing: JavaScript; PHP
XML Processing: Use as a database

| Final Exam/Project

Projects and Grading

There will be an ongoing set of programming assignments during the semester. Small assignments will be graded on an "OK"—"Not OK" basis, while larger assignments will be graded on a 10–point scale. The number and sizes of the assignments varies from semester to semester, but in aggregate you can expect them to count 30–40% of your course grade. The midterm and final exams will count equally for the remainder of your grade. Exams are based on concepts and programming techniques required for doing the assignments.

To receive full credit for programming assignments, they must be correct and submitted by midnight of their announced due dates. Assignments submitted up to one week after they are due will receive up to half credit. After one week, no credit will be given but assignments may still be submitted for feedback. Assignments are typically cumulative, so it is generally necessary to complete all assignments, even if their deadlines are missed.

Vickery Home XHTML CSS Last updated .